Welcome back.
This is Kimberly.
You haven't seen me in a little while,
but you're not going to see me now either.
The focus is on the slides right now.
All right, so you will not see my video in
these.
So Assad just covered what our points are
for earned value.
So we can calculate budget at completion,
planned value, actual costs, earned value,
and then forecast.
All right.
So based on these, let's look at the next
slide.
Here's an example.
You need to be able to pull out those
points.
So you're remodeling a small office
building.
Renovations include bathroom upgrades,
replacing carpet in the halls,
upgrading lighting on 10 floors.
We have 10 floors.
Each floor is expected to take one week.
So how long will the whole project take
us?
10 weeks.
Each floor is expected to cost 60,000.
So how much will the whole project cost
us?
Budget at completion, 10 times the 60,000.
So I need you to be able to see these and
pull this information out.
the project is four weeks in so at week
four we're doing a performance review this
will be our planned value at week four how
much work did we plan to get done and of
course we had to pay for it so four times
sixty thousand that's what i want you to
see that's our planned value at week four
costs are 280,000 to date these are your
actual costs so that was given and then
we're told we have 4.5 floors that have
been completed that is your earned value
so what have we completed the work we've
completed 4.5 times 60,000 so those are
what I need you to be able to pull out of
a scenario all right and then we'll look
at this last one this will be used for
forecasting so we'll assume future
performance would be typical of the past
so let's look at the actual formulas so we
have budget at completion we have the 10
floors times the 60,000
per week okay so we plan
expect the entire project
to cost us $600,000.
That is our entire cost baseline, all our
estimated costs plus contingency reserves.
Planned value.
Again, we're at week four.
60,000 per week per floor is $240,000.
Our actual cost, $280,000 that was given.
Earned value, 4.5 floors we've completed.
We've completed.
at the 60,000.
So we've completed 270,000 worth of work.
Think the work we've completed.
You're going to see everything is compared
to earned value.
Everything.
Earned value compared to planned value.
Think time.
Earned value compared to your actual
costs.
Think costs, of course.
Okay, so again, everything is compared to
earned value if earned value is higher in
one of the other points we are happy if it
is lower we are not happy I'm using my
mouse so excuse the the scribble
all right so earn value compared
to our plan value time so we've
completed 270,000 words of
work we planned expected
to complete 240,000.
So we are happy with our time.
We've completed 270,000 worth of work
compared to we have spent 280,000.
So with our costs, we're not happy.
Always know that first.
Then we'll calculate.
So I know Asad already mentioned the
formulas.
We're going to jump right in them based on
what we know.
We're happy with our schedule.
We're not happy with our costs.
So our cost variance earned value minus
actual costs.
Our variance is negative.
Confirming we're not happy.
So our variance is negative 10,000.
That's exactly how far off we are.
We're 10,000 over budget.
Our cost performance index earned value
over your actual costs.
We're performing at 96%.
We know we are not happy with our costs.
So this confirms it.
Now, you have to be
able to describe to your
stakeholders what a cost
performance index means.
They don't know.
So you have to be able to
translate that and say, this means
we are earning 96 cents for
every dollar we're spending.
So that's not horrible.
So we can probably correct this,
okay?
But this is our performance confirming
we're not happy with our schedule.
Let's look at the next slide.
Our schedule variants, we know we were
happy with our schedule.
So our schedule variance earned value
minus plan value of course is positive.
We've completed 30,000 more than we
planned.
At the this point in time.
Our schedule performance index earned
value over plan value.
We know we're happy with our schedule.
We know we're performing it over 100%.
So this confirms it.
With our schedule, we're performing at
112%.
So we're 12% ahead of schedule.
Based on this.
And again, going back
to that original slide,
assume future performance will be typical.
similar of the past.
So we will forecast estimate at
completion.
How much is the whole project going to cost
us based on our performance continuing?
So you have budget at completion over your
cost performance index.
Of course it will cost us more to do all
the work because our cost performance has
not been good and we expect that to
continue.
So our estimate at completion will be
625,000.
Estimate to complete ETC, how much is it
going to cost us to
finish the remaining work?
So we have our new forecast estimate at
completion minus actual costs.
So to complete the rest of the work,
it's going to cost us $345,000.
Variance at completion
is the difference between
our original budget at
completion and our forecast.
So, of course, it's going
to be negative because
our costs have been
performance has been negative.
So negative 25,000 over budget.
And last but not least, TCPI to complete
performance index.
How well do we have
to perform from this point
forward to meet our original
budget at completion?
So that's budget at completion minus
certain value over budget at completion.
completion minus your actual cost.
So from this point forward, we're at week
four.
From here forward, we have
to perform at 103% to be able
to meet our original budget
at completion of 600,000.
So you have to be able to know what these
answers mean.
You might not actually have to calculate.
So are we performing well with our
schedule?
Sure, we are.
We're ahead of schedule.
Are we performing well with our costs?
Nope.
Again, this is confirming what we know.
So our cost performance is not good.
All right, so those are
the big things you have
to be able to pull out
if you see an example.
Is our project performance healthy with
our costs?
and with our schedule.